Finding Aid for Henry Chandler Cowles lantern slide collection, 1898-1936
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Chandler Cowles lantern slide collection 1898-1936
Cowles, Henry Chandler
2009051 Aa 2
The Henry Chandler Cowles photograph collection is comprised primarily of lantern slides. As a botany professor at the University of Chicago, Cowles led several field trips to observe ecological environments during the years from 1898 to 1934. The lantern slides in this collection cover the geographic areas of Michigan, Colorado, Indiana, Wisconsin, and Illinois and include photographic subjects such as dunes, plant life, forests, landscapes, and class group pictures.
104 slides in 3 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received from the Matthaei Botanical Gardens (donor no. 6701 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Henry Chandler Cowles came to the University of Chicago as a graduate student in 1895 to study under John M. Coulter a noted botanist at the newly formed university. Cowles's Ph.D. thesis entitled "The Ecological Relations of the Vegetation on the Sand Dunes of Lake Michigan" completed in 1898 detailed Cowles's theory on plant evolution in relation to geographic situation. That is, the closer one moves inland the more advanced along the evolutionary chain the plant species become.[1] Cowles based his thesis on observations made along Lake Michigan in Dune Park, Indiana. His thesis was published in Botanical Gazette in 1899 and its popularity led to Cowles becoming known as the first professional ecologist.[2] Cowles published The Physiographic Ecology of Chicago and Vicinity; A Study of the Origin, Development, and Classification of Plant Societies (1901) two years later that furthered his theory of plant succession and constant state of evolution.
Cowles began teaching at the University of Chicago in 1897 and initiated field trips with his classes in order to study ecological sites. The earliest trips were to Dune Park, Indiana the same location Cowles used in his thesis. Later excursions took place in Michigan, Indiana, Alaska, Colorado, and Maine, among others. The most common classes to include field excursions were Cowles's Elementary Ecology (Botany 3, Botany 203), Field Ecology (Botany 36, Botany 336) and Physiographic Ecology (Botany 34, Botany 234, Botany 334).[3]
Beginning in September 1898 with a trip to North Manitou Island, Cowles's field ecology classes made several trips to Michigan that continued sporadically through about 1923.[4] Cowles and associates including George D. Fuller and W.J. Cribs photographed the plants, dunes, forests, plants, trees, and students on these trips. These photographs illustrate interesting ecological and environmental elements in their original settings and over time. Cowles became chair of the department in 1925 and retired from the university in 1934. He passed away in 1939.
The University of Chicago Special Collections (http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/) holds many of the originals photographs. An effort has been made by the Library of Congress's American Memory project to digitize many of Cowles's photographs. see: http://lcweb2.loc.gov/ammem/collections/ecology/index.html.
_________________
Notes:
"Ecology and the American Environment" http://lcweb2.loc.gov/ammem/collections/ecology/aepsp4.html
ibid.
ibid.
"Chronology of Field Trips 1898-1934" http://lcweb2.loc.gov/ammem/collections/ecology/aepchron5.html
The Henry Chandler Cowles photograph collection is comprised primarily of glass lantern slides from Cowles's ecology trips covering the years 1898 to 1936 with the majority being unmarked or falling between the years 1900-1912. Captions affixed to the plates are noted when available along with any numbering. Some of the handwriting is difficult to make out as are the Latin names of the plants but every attempt at correct spelling has been made. The collection is divided into seven series: Michigan Photographs, Colorado Photographs, Illinois Photographs, Indiana Photographs, Wisconsin Photographs, Miscellaneous Photographs, and Indiana Transparencies. Each state has subseries of General -- which indicates a many single location photographs -- and subseries of cities for which a group of photographs exists.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cowles, Henry Chandler, 1869-1939.; Ecology--Michigan.; Forests and forestry--Michigan.; Sand dunes--Environmental aspects--Michigan.; Shorelines--Great Lakes Region (North America); Classes (Groups of Students); Kalamazoo River (Mich.); Keweenaw Peninsula (Mich.)
Contributors:
Cribbs, William Johnston.; Fuller, George Damon.; Teeri, James.
Genre Terms:
Lantern slides.; Photographs.
- Michigan Photographs
  The Michigan Photographs series (1906-1933 and undated) is arranged by geographic location. The series has 11 subseries. The General series encompasses those slides with single instances of geographic location; the remaining subseries are cities themselves from which a group of photographs exist.
  - General
    - Acer Saccharum, Struck by lightning in midst of forest. Splinters thrown 100 ft. or more. Michigan. (Box 1)
    - Ammophilio breviligulato on foredune (new) old gravel beach -- erosional dune slope with Pinus., Onekama, Michigan. (Box 1)
    - Dune complex advancing over mesic forest. Ammophilo Calomovilfo in foreground on lee slope,. Ludington, Michigan. September 13, 1916 (Box 1)
    - Equisetum hyemale North of Palisade Park, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh 49.2] J.G. Brown.)
    - Former outlet of White Lake now closed by dune. Michilinda, Michigan (Box 1)
      ([SW 3])
    - Pinus Strobus projecting above Tsuga, Acer, Fagus, etc. Primeval. Huron Mts., Michigan. (Box 1)
    - Populus deltoids with roots from trunk, Muskegon, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh Z51])
    - Secondary Pop. Trem., Betula alba -- Aqate Harbor Trail, Keweenaw. Peninsula., Mich. (Box 1)
      ([U 25.41] W.S. Dudgeen, G.D. Fuller)
    - Stumps of former (Acer) maple forest L Hancock, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([U 37])
    - Succession of Mosses on Isle Royale (Box 1)
      ([SW 51.0] Geo. D. Fuller)
    - Sunset. Lake Michigan. 1910 (Box 1)
      ([G.F. 2])
    - Thuja with roots from buried trunk Charlevox, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh 85.02] Geo. D. Fuller)
    - Wind sweeps thru perched dunes. So. Fox Is. Mich. Showing gravel in floor of sweep (Box 1)
      ([Esn 5.25])
    - W.J Cribbs camp at Point Betsie, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([B 123.8] A156, W.J. Cribbs.)
    - Wreck at Robinson's Folly. Mackinac, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Mich. No. 2])
  - Bay View
    - Ecological Field class 1915 Bay View, Michigan (Box 1)
      ([B 115] Geo D. Fuller. [U82.65])
    - Fagus, acer, Tsuga forest Bay View, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Dte 5.01] Geo. D. Fuller)
  - Douglas Lake, Michigan
    - Cladonia spp. on sandy soil -- burned areas in aspens Douglas Lake, Michigan (Box 1)
      ([89])
    - Douglas Lake, Michigan 1911-paper birch and aspen -- with understanding of Abies balsaoned, Acer sacchous, Betub luteo, etc,. 1933 (Box 1)
    - Drossero rotundifolio, Douglas Lake, Michigan (Box 1)
      ([85?])
    - Thuja Swamp. Douglas Lake, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([SW 40.32] AA Nichols)
  - Frankfort, Michigan
    - Conifer heath on dune "The crater" 1915. Frankfort, Michigan (Box 1)
    - Monotropa uniflora. Frankfort, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Fl 105])
    - Tsuga canadensis, Fagus grandifolio and Betula lutes on dunes, Frankfort, Michigan August 11, 1915 (Box 1)
    - Tsuga, Fagus, etc. on fixed dune. Frankfort, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh 84.01] no. 2 Geo. D. Fuller)
    - Tsuga forest on dunes, Frankfort, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh Z5!])
  - Glen Haven, Michigan
    - 1906 Ecological field party. Glen Haven, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([B106])
    - Around the fire Glen Haven, Mich. [G.F. 16] (Box 1)
    - Kame(?) Cliffs. Sleeping Bear dune sin b.g.(?) Glen Haven, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Est 20])
    - Landslide Face of Sleeping Bear Point, Glen Haven, Michigan. August 16, 1915 (Box 1)
    - Thuja graveyard. Old soil lines Sleeping Bear Point, Glen Haven, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh Z52])
  - Little Point Sable, Michigan
    - Dune advancing into Silver Lake Little Point Sable, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh 56.4])
    - Dune advancing into Silver Lake. Little Point Sable, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh 56.5])
    - Forest graveyard, (Pinus strobus) Little Point Sable, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Xsh 52.8])
  - Munising, Michigan (Grand Island)
    - Climax Forest almost pure Acer saccharum. Lawson, Munising Ry, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Dte 1.3] W.S. Dudgeon. Geo D. Fuller)
    - P. Strobus -- detail of trunk. Grand, Isd. Munising, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([F 5.2] W.S. Dudgeon. Geo. D. Fuller.)
    - Tsuga Can. detail of trunk Grand Isd., Munising, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([F51.2] W.S. Dudgeon. Geo. D. Fuller.)
    - Tsuga can. seedlings growing on log Climax Forest Grand Isd., Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Dte 20.1] W.S. Dudgeon. Geo. D. Fuller)
  - Saugatuck, Michigan
    - Dr. Fuller and class. 1918. Saugatuck, Michigan. (Box 1)
      ([B118] Fuller)
    - Fagus on eroding dune Sagautuck, Mich. [ (Box 1)
      (Esh 23.20] Fuller)
    - Foredune and Populus delfoides near dredged outlet of Kalamazoo River, Saugatuck, Michigan 1916 (Box 1)
  - Sawyer, Michigan
    - Established hemlock (Tsuge Canadensis) and moving dune. Sawyer, Michigan (Box 1)
      ([XSh 53.3])
    - Moving dune Mesic forest in foreground, Sawyer, Michigan May 20, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Soo Locks-Michigan
    - American Lock, Closed. Soo, A. [Mich No. 7] (Box 1)
    - American Lock with raft & tug, Soo Am. [Mich. No. 8] (Box 1)
    - Map showing St. Marie's River and the Soo, Mich. (Box 1)
      ([Mich. No. 6])
  - Three Oaks, Michigan
    - Elm -- buttressed. 1911 Three Oaks, Mich. Geo D. fuller (Box 1)
      ([Dte 6.6])
    - Plantus occidentalis trunk. Three Oaks, Michigan November 5, 1910 (Box 1)
- Colorado Photographs
  The Colorado Photograph series (1914-1928 and undated) is arranged by geographic location. The series has two subseries. The General series encompasses those slides with single instances of geographic location; the remaining subseries is a city from which a group of photographs exist.
  - General
    - Ready for Long's Peak, Colo August 1925 (Box 2)
      ([B125.1])
    - Grassland following burned forest 10,000 ft. Mammoth Gulch, Colo. 1928 (Box 2)
    - Class in Field Ecology,. Eslis Park, Colo., Summer 1914 (Box 2)
      ([B114.0])
    - Succession in grasslands of South Boulder Park, Colo. (Box 2)
      ([P0.78])
    - Dry grass and meadow. Tolland Colo. (Box 2)
      ([P0.75])
    - Narrows, Long Peak Colo. (Box 2)
      ([Colo 16.2])
  - Akron, Colorado
    - Weighing apparatus for water requirements Akron, Colo. (Box 2)
      ([P0.43])
    - Meteorological instruments Supt. Grace at right. Akron, Ohio. (Box 2)
      ([P 0.415])
    - Akron, Col. Water requirements station (Box 2)
      ([P0.42] Geo. D. Fuller [13-60])
    - Frames for shading Akron, Colo. (Box 2)
      ([P0.44])
    - I.P.E. short grass plain Akron, Colo. (Box 2)
      ([P0.20] Geo. D. Fuller [13-46])
    - James Peak[Long is crossed out] summit 14255 1914. Colo. (Box 2)
      ([Colo 15])
    - Pinus aristata P. flegilis 11,500 ft. James Peak, Colo. (Box 2)
      ([Mt25.330] Worthley. Fuller)
- Illinois Photographs
  - General
    - Evaporation averages. Chicago, Ill. (Box 2)
      ([P0.15] Fuller)
    - Wading sloughs of the Mississippi. Rock Island, Ill. (Box 2)
      ([B123.7] [A47] W.J. Cribbs)
- Indiana Photographs
  The Indiana Photograph series (1901-1936 and undated) is arranged by geographic location. The series has 7 subseries. The General series encompasses those slides with single instances of geographic location; the remaining subseries are cities themselves from which a group of photographs exist.
  - General
    - Slough #58 Summer. Buffington, Indiana (Box 2)
    - Beach Dune. Cheltenham, Indiana (Box 2)
    - Old swamp soil exposed by erosion of superjacent dune. Michigan City, Indiana. (Box 2)
      ([Esh 57.5])
  - Chesterton, Indiana
    - Dune advance on Pinus strobes Qucerus, etc. Chesterton, Indiana. 190? (Box 2)
    - General View of established dune. Chesterton, Indiana (Box 2)
      ([Xsn82])
  - Dune Park, Indiana
    - Loading dunes on cars. Dune Park, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Xsh 243])
    - Embryo dunes -- recent line of Populus deltoids -- older beach edges with Populus deltoids background, Dune Park, Indiana. 1904 (Box 2)
    - Rhizome of Juneus balticus. Dune Park, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Xsh64])
    - Advancing dune complex winter. Dune Park, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Xsh 58.2])
    - Blowout crater. Dune Park, Indiana. September 18, 1910 (Box 2)
    - "The Crater" Dune Park, Indiana (Box 2)
      ([Xsh241])
    - Dunes advancing 1901. Dune Park, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Xsh 93.0] Fuller. Meyers)
    - Ammophila. Foredune Grand Beach, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Xsh 10.34])
  - Millers, Indiana
    - Treceasi, McDougall, Cowles. Millers, Indiana. (Box 2)
      ([B20.5])
    - Populus deltodius seedlins-280-#2. 11 inches to water. Miller, Indiana. August 22, 1936. (Box 2)
  - Mineral Springs, Indiana
    - Depositing shores. Mineral Springs, Ind. October 19, 1919 (Box 2)
      ([Xsh3.2] P.J. Sedgwick.)
    - Cornus Canadensis. Mineral Springs, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Fi 103.1])
    - Cypripedium aeaule Mineral Springs, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Sw47.5] Huntington)
    - Maianthe mum canadense. Mineral Springs, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Dte 13.5] Huntington.)
  - Port Chester, Indiana
    - Pinus strobes graveyard. Port Chester Indiana August 1910 (Box 2)
    - Roots from trunk of Tilia. Portchester, Ind. (Box 2)
      ([Xsh92.0])
  - Otis, Indiana
    - Trillium grandiflorum. Otis, Ind. Huntington (Box 2)
      ([Dte 13.4])
    - Beech -- Maple forest, Otist, Indiana. (Box 2)
      ([Dte4.2])
    - Beech -- Maple forest on clay -- valparaino moraine, Otis, Indiana. May 30, 1910 (Box 2)
    - Gully erosion in Valparaiso maraine formerly beech-maple forest, Otis, Indiana. May 30, 1910 (Box 2)
- Wisconsin Photographs
  - General
    - Bot. 36 1919 Door Co. Wis. (Box 2)
      ([B119.6] Sedgwick)
    - Bot. 36 1919. Europe Lake. Door Co. Wis. 1919 (Box 2)
      ([B119.1] Sedgwick)
    - Class at noon day rest. Door Co. Wisc. 191 (Box 2)
      ([B119.93] Sedgwick)
    - Door Co. Wis. 1919 (Box 2)
      ([B119.5] Sedgwick)
- Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 2)
  The Miscellaneous Photograph series (1910-1922 and undated) is arranged alphabetically and encompasses those photographs of a general nature for which little or no information about location or context exists.
  - Diagram of dune movement (Box 2)
    ([Xsh 62.0]. Diagram illustrating how a sand dune migrates. A.A. Hansen)
  - Eroding Mesophytic Forest dune north of Palisade Park (Box 2)
    (. J.G. Brown [Xsh 98.2])
  - Evaporation averages 1910-1911 (Box 2)
    ([11] Ind. 11)
  - Forest Distribution (Box 2)
    ([Dte 0] Nichols)
  - Habenaria orbisculata in B.M.H Forest. Palisades Park (Box 2)
    ([Xsh 83.7] J.G. Brown)
  - H.C. Cowles. J.P. Lotey 1922 (Box 2)
  - Physiographic Ecology class summer quarter 1910 (Box 2)
    ([B110.0])
  - Physiographic Ecology Class 1912 (Box 2)
    ([B112.2])
  - Tsuga log showing effect of suppression. (Box 2)
    ([F51.1])
  - Ulmus Americana -- sections of leaves 18 -- Mesophyticform: 19, dune form. (Box 2)
    ([L5.4] Geo. D. Fuller)
- Indiana Transparencies
  The Indiana Transparencies series (1897-1934) contains transparencies copies of photographs from Cowles's excursions to Indiana and mostly comprised of those taken in Dune Park, Indiana.
  - Transparencies (Box 3)
Related Material
The University of Chicago Special Collections (http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/) holds many of the original photographs. An effort has been made by the Library of Congress's American Memory project to digitize many of Cowles's photographs. see: http://lcweb2.loc.gov/ammem/collections/ecology/index.html.